...
Welcome to 600.2x.
I'm John Guttag, a professor of electrical engineering
and computer science at MIT, and I'll be lecturing this course.
Actually, I'll be doing almost all of the lectures, not all.
There'll be one guest lecture by Eric Grimson,
who some of you may remember fondly from 600.1x.
Before we start the course, you probably
want to know what do I expect you to know
at the beginning of the course?
Well, the first thing I expect you to know is how to program.
More specifically, I expect you to know how
to program in Python.
Ideally, you'll have written a program of at least 150 lines.
Don't panic if the biggest program you've written
is 100 lines, maybe even 90 lines, 70 lines.
But if you're not comfortable, if you're
struggling writing simple programs,
this is not the course for you.
We're assuming you already know how to program,
and that you already know how to program in Python.
As it says in the slide, we teach the course in Python 3.5.
And clearly, if you've programmed in that,
that's advantageous.
No need to worry if your experience is in 2.6, 2.7.
The differences are very minimal between the versions
of the language.
And you won't have any trouble catching on.
We also expect you to have some familiarity
with the basic concepts of computational complexity.
We'll be looking at some interesting programs
in this course and talking about whether they're
practical or not practical.
Whether a program is practical often
depends upon its performance.
Will it run fast enough to actually give you
an answer in a timely way?
In order to understand those things,
you need to understand a bit about complexity.
Not the details, I don't expect you to have
taken an algorithms course.
But I do expect you to know the difference
between a linear algorithm, a polynomial logarithm,
and an exponential algorithm.
Along those lines, we expect some familiarity
with simple algorithms, things like binary search, merge sort.
If you have taken 600.1x, you're golden.
That contains more than you need to take this course.
If you haven't, well, then, you need
to know the things I've just been talking about.
Those of you who have taken 600.1x are probably wondering
how do the courses differ?
How do they compare to each other?
Well first, some good news.
I think you'll find the programming assignments a bit
easier than 600.1x, not because they're intrinsically easier,
but because you're a better programmer than you were when
you started 600.1x.
Also, I think what you'll find is that you struggle
less with the actual coding and maybe more
with understanding the concepts that you
are trying to implement.
And that's in keeping with what this course is about.
The focus is more on the problem to be
solved than on the actual programming of the solution.
For that reason, the lectures are more abstract than they
were in 600.1x.
We're not going to say, here's this syntax of a FOR statement.
Here is what happens when the variable is changed.
Instead, we'll be talking about computation
in a more general way, problems in a more general way,
and how do we use computation to do something
that we truly care about?
One way to think about it is the course
is less about programming and more
about dipping your toe into those very interesting waters
of data science.
As pretty much everyone knows, today the data
is arriving with the world in a ferocious rate.
Unfortunately, data scientists are not
arriving in the world at a ferocious rate.
And so we're way behind in having
people who can keep up with the data and build useful things
with the data, extract useful information from it.
When you've finished this course,
you're not going to be a data scientist.
But you will have dipped your toe in that world
and be ready to learn more.
Why should you take this course?
Well, one, to become a better programmer, and two,
to begin to learn about making more productive use of data,
both how to think about data, and m statistically,
and how to use packages to make the programming easier.
All of that said, all of our emphasis on concepts,
there's still a big element of honing your programming skills.
Nobody becomes an expert programmer taking one course.
This course will help you solidify what you already
know about programming.
I will be introducing a few additional bits of Python
that were not covered in 600.1.
Not too much.
You'll have to bear with me.
I'm a software engineer by training.
I'll be delivering some sermons about programming
and how to write better software.
As I've already mentioned, we'll be showing you
some useful packages.
But a lot of what will make you a better programmer
can be traced to, well, let me tell a story about this.
What you see here is a picture of Carnegie Hall,
one of the world's most famous concert halls.
It's in New York City.
One day a tourist late for a concert
is desperately searching for Carnegie Hall,
finds a policeman, goes up to the policeman,
frantically says, tell me, how do you get to Carnegie Hall?
The policeman looks at the tourist and says, that's easy.
Practice, practice, and more practice.
And that's how you become a good programmer.
What will you be practicing on?
What you'll be practicing on is building computational models.
Well, what is a computational model?
It's a device that helps us use computation to help understand
the world in which we live.
One way to think about it is as an experimental device
that can be used to help us understand something that's
already happened, or often more usefully, to predict something
that might happen in the future.
I like to draw an analogy to laboratory experiments.
When I was an undergraduate, what an experiment meant
was go into a laboratory, get your hands dirty,
breathe horrible fumes, maybe, in a chemistry lab
even though you weren't supposed to, and do an experiment.
Well, physical labs are not going to go away.
But they've certainly been supplemented these days
by virtual labs where we do the experiment not in a lab,
but on a computer.
And we learn an awful lot from doing
at least initial experiments that way.
So what kind of experimental devices are there?
There are optimization models, we'll
talk about those, statistical models, and simulation models.
All of these kinds of models are used a lot in practice.
Insurance companies, for example,
build models of customers that are
used to predict future claims, and thus, to price policies.
Doctors have models that predict normal laboratory readings
for patients and raise alarms when
a test is outside those bounds.
Google Maps, Apple Maps, Waze, etc.,
model possible routes between places as graphs,
and solve a graph optimization problem
to find what they claim will be an optimal route.
Cell phone providers build models
to predict how their service will
behave under various conditions and use these models to decide
where to put in new towers.
Biochemists build models of molecular interactions
that allow them to perform in silico, rather than in vivo,
experiments.
Mostly in this course, we'll look at models
that involve uncertainty.
But that's not where we'll start.
We'll start in lecture 1 with optimization models.
We will, as I said earlier, be giving you
problem sets to work on.
These are programming problems designed
to help you become a better programmer
and also to test your understanding
of the conceptual material, actually not really so much
to test it, as to help you solidify your understanding
of the conceptual material.
There will also be some small finger exercises.
These are programming problems designed
to cover just really one concept at a time
and help you learn those concepts.
There'll be reading assignments.
These are pretty important.
There'll be a lot of important concepts
that I'll touch on in the lectures
but not really explain as fully as maybe you would like.
And we'll be giving you reading assignments
to catch up on that.
The reading assignments will all be in the course text.
And here's good news for at least some of you.
If you took 600.1x, at least in the last iteration,
it's the same textbook.
You don't have to go buy a new one.
And finally, of course, there will be exams.
And those will be based upon the programming
problems, the finger exercises, and the reading.